Curriculum Vitae - Stephen Giles

Email: <u>s.giles@hotmail.co.uk</u>Phone: +44 7957 196965LinkedIn: <u>Stephen Giles</u>

About

In September 2014 I embarked on a 12 Week Coding Bootcamp with <u>Makers Academy</u>, which represented a big change in career path and lifestyle. Apart from two C++ Modules completed ten years earlier as part of my Mathematics Degree this was a new challenge and one in which I would learn a lot.

I thoroughly enjoyed the course and the intellectual stimulation that coding provided. With a background in Mathematics, my ability to problem solve and think logically helped me to tackle some aspects of these newly acquired skills. The course was primarily based around Ruby and JavaScript, and I felt that my strengths were coding the 'back-end logic' as well as debugging when errors occurred. That said, the 'front-end' was also something that I found enjoyable and interesting, in particularly working with jQuery.

The sections below should provide more information about what I have achieved prior to this change, but also provide an insight to some of the work and projects I have completed in the last 12 weeks. I am very aware that I have experienced only the tip of a very big iceburg that is 'coding' and am now seeking employment which will allow me to continue to learn and development my skills - whether that be in Web Development, App Development or Software Development.

Education

Makers Academy (September 2014 - December 2014)

A 12 Week Immersive Coding Bootcamp. Here I spent 12 weeks learning how to code primarily based around the Ruby and JavaScript languages. I used HTML, CSS and jQuery on the front-end to build Web Applications initially using Sinatra and then Rails. As well as this, I also spent a week learning Swift and Xcode to produce a native iOS App. PostgreSQL was the database used for the majority of projects (with Active Record and DataMapper). Makers Academy are very effective at teaching TDD and I used RSpec, Cabybara and Jasmine for testing. We used Git for version control and various APIs including Twilio, GitHub, FaceBook and GoogleMaps. I also had some experience with Node.js, Express, Socket.io and Sass.

St. Mary's University College, Twickenham (September 2007 - July 2008)

- Postgraduate Certificate in Education
- Secondary: KS3, KS4 and Post 16
- Subject: Mathematics

Royal Holloway, University of London (September 2002 - June 2005)

Mathematics BSc. (Hons) 2:1

The Campion School and Sixth Form (September 1994 - August 2001)

- A-Levels: Mathematics (A), English Literature (C), Biology (C), General Studies (B)
- GCSEs: 1 A*, 7 As, 2 Bs

Work Experience

Woking High School, Woking, Surrey (July 2008 - August 2014)

Assistant Principal, Director of Maths and English, Head of Maths, Maths Teacher

During my PGCE (Teacher Training) in 2007-2008, I completed a placement at Woking High School. During this time they offered me a full-time post as Maths Teacher starting immediately after my training had finished. Woking High is a mixed comprehesive for 1200 11-16 year olds. Upon my arrival, *just over 40% of students achieved an A*-C in their Mathematics GCSE*.

During my first year as a qualified teacher, I was offered the role as Head of Maths. After one year in this role I spent two years as Director of Maths. I then spent the final two years as an Assistant Principal responsible for Maths and English. During my time at Woking High School, Mathematics GCSE results improved every year and in my final year, 81% of students achieved an A*-C in their Mathematics GCSE.

Key Responsibilities

- Teaching Mathematics
- Managing Teams of Staff from Departmental to Whole School level
- Tracking and monitoring the progress of students
- Monitoring, supporting and training Staff
- Communication with parents
- Organising events, residentials, councils, meetings and INSET training

Venn Group, Slough, Berkshire (November 2006 - July 2007)

Recruitment Consultant

Venn Group specialise in Contract and Temporary Recruitment within the Finance Sector. During my time at Venn Group I was responsible for sourcing roles from clients and then finding and placing candidates in these roles and other roles within the office.

Bar163 (Chertsey) and The Glasshouse (Kew) (July 2005 - November 2006)

Restaurant Manager

From the age of 18 I had always worked behind a bar and was a Duty Manager at Medicine Bar on the Royal Holloway University Campus. When I completed my degree I spent almost 18 months working as a Restaurant Manager.

Brentwood Diocese (September 2001 - July 2002)

Youth Worker

I spent a gap year between A-Levels and University working with young people within the Brentwood Diocese.

Skills and Languages

Coding (in order of experience/strength)

Languages	Frameworks	Testing	Other
Ruby	Rails	RSpec	PostgreSQL
JavaScript	Sinatra	Jasmine	Git
jQuery	Express on Node.js	Capybara	Heroku
HTML5		Cucumber	Xcode
CSS3			Parse
Swift			PhoneGap
Sass			

Various APIs also used including: GitHub, GoogleMaps, Twilio, FaceBook, LinkedIn, Stripe, AWS

Other

- Teaching
- Management
- Communication
- Organisation

Code and Project Examples

All of my GitHub repositories can be <u>found here</u>. Below are some highlights of projects I completed or was part of. All links go to the repository unless stated otherwise. Hopefully they show the progression over the 12 weeks.

At Makers Academy we completed a Final Project during Weeks 11 and 12. In a team of four, we produced three different Apps:

- pointr A native iOS App created using Swift and Xcode. You can find your friends and send them 'points' just for fun! You can view the <u>demonstration</u> video here.
- <u>badgr</u> A cross-platform Mobile App created using PhoneGap with HTML, CSS, JavaScript and jQuery. Based on the Yo App, however, rather than sending a Yo you can send them a badge! You can view the <u>demonstration</u> video here.
- Rewardr A Web App created using Ruby on Rails with HTML, CSS and jQuery on the front-end. This is a corporate themed App where a company can reward their employees with a Reward. You can view the site here.

During a three day Makerthon (Week 9 of 12), as part of a team of four, we produced <u>Jumparound</u>. This was a site to help one of our cohort members locate his missing jumper. The site can be <u>viewed here</u>. We used Ruby on Rails with HTML, CSS, jQuery and Bootstrap. We also used the GoogleMaps API and gmaps.js.

Rock, Paper, Scissors Version 1 - This version was written in Ruby using just HTML and CSS on the front-end during Week 4. Play it here.

Rock, Paper, Scissors Version 2 - This was written in JavaScript with jQuery on the front-end during Week 6. Play it here.

I also wrote four Ruby Gems during Week 10. time_until_break was a basic gem for my cohort to run in their terminal to find out how long was left until our daily break. I then produced create_awesome_readme that creates a well-structured README template for your projects. Lastly I created make_me_a_gem_called that creates all the necessary files for people to write a gem themselves. I really enjoyed playing around with these and hope to continue making more in the future.

Personal Interests and Information

I consider myself a hard-working and dedicated individual who enjoys both learning and teaching new skills. I am also ambitious as I hope can be seen from the progression in my Work Experience, particularly in Education. I have management skills from both Education and Hospitality. I hope that all of these skills and qualities will allow me to continue to be successful within the IT sector.

I love food and drink and really enjoy cooking. This is from my time working in bars and restaurants and has continued to be a passion of mine. I am also a keen sports fan. I played rugby from the age of 11 up to 25 and was Captain at Egham Rugby Club in my final season.